Welcome to AP US History Unit 8. This
unit covers the time period 1945 to 1980
in American history and it is worth
about 10 to 17% on your AP exam. For any
who need to know, this video is simply a
clip together video of all my APUSH Unit
8 topic review videos without the AP
style questions at the end of each
video. If you'd like to attempt the
questions at the end of the videos, my
full Unit 8 review playlist will be in
the description. A reminder to please
follow my Instagram if you guys don't
mind, but anyway, let's get into Unit 8.
So, World War II is now over and the end
of this war will see the rise of two
major global superpowers, the Soviet
Union and the United States. The thing
is, these two superpowers were allies
during World War II and pretty much
immediately after the war, their
alliance collapses. The reason for this
is pretty simple, these two countries'
ideologies are completely different.
Over in the US, we have democracy,
capitalism, and free markets. However,
going over to the Soviet Union, we now
have a system known as authoritarian
communism, which means the state
controls literally everything. So, you
might think that these two countries are
going to go to war, but the world just
went through a horribly devastating war
and now things like nuclear weapons
exist. If another war were to happen,
it's not unreasonable to say that the
world could quite literally come to an
end. So, the thing that emerges, the
Cold War, isn't a normal war at all. It
will be a 45-year long series of smaller
conflicts and tensions that, over time,
add up to one massive, quote, Cold War.
So, from 1945 to 1980, one thing will
remain constant, containment. Simply
meaning that the US's goal is to stop
communism from spreading. This idea
comes from George Kennan's Long
Telegram, where he argues that the
Soviet Union will expand unless firmly
contained. So, let's give some examples
of this containment. First is economic
aid. The Truman Doctrine will be made,
declaring the US will give money to
Greece and Turkey to stop communist
influence. Also, the Marshall Plan will
be enacted to send billions of dollars
to rebuild Western Europe after the war.
But, the second thing here is military
alliances. Western democracies will ally
under the North Atlantic Treaty
Organization, or NATO, and later the
Soviet Union will respond and create the
Warsaw Pact for all of its countries.
And now notice that with these new
organizations, the world is essentially
split in half. Finally, the last thing
here will be military conflicts. This is
where we see proxy wars like the Korean
War and looking at this, basically North
Korea is communist and wants to invade
the democratic South Korea. The US will
ally with the South, the communist China
will ally with the North, and the war
happens and after three years it will
end in a draw. Cool. Then, the Cuban
Missile Crisis will have the Soviets
place nuclear missiles in Cuba, the US
blockades Cuba, the world nearly ends,
but all is good after some negotiation.
But, by the 1970s, this Cold War had
really gone on for long enough. Vietnam
is something that we'll cover later in
this unit, but let's just say that the
US was not having a great time in
Vietnam. Under Nixon, various treaties
and open communications between the US
and China \slash} the Soviet Union will
happen. And the key method of the Cold
War will now turn to something called
detente, meaning to ease tensions. There
are also so many other parts of this
Cold War that I do not have time to go
over. Just understand that the US used a
lot of different strategies over the
years to manage the Soviet threat. On
the Cold War, it isn't exactly limited
to conflicts with the Soviet Union. I
mean, yes, that is the definition on
paper, but the Cold War will also cause
a lot of things to happen specifically
in America. Specifically for this video,
I want to talk to you about the Red
Scare. But before that, let's head over
to post-World War II Europe. Despite the
US's efforts to contain communism, in
1949, the Soviet Union gets an atomic
bomb. And also in 1949, China will
become communist. And right after that,
in 1950, the Korean War starts. With all
this happening so quickly, fear began to
grow that communism might reach the
United States. And that fear will cause
an era known as the second big Red
Scare, where anti-communist paranoia in
America will lead to blacklisting,
ruined reputations, and widespread
intimidation. And the big person I want
to mention here is a senator named
Joseph [music] McCarthy. And for all you
Gen Z kids, this man is the perfect
definition of a rage baiter. He
basically claimed communists were
everywhere in the government, but often
had little to no evidence to back it up.
And I think this perfectly encapsulates
this era, because now we see accusations
of communism without any proof, careers
being destroyed left and right as a
result, and all of it really just
leading to a massive public fear. And
this will also lead to serious limits on
civil liberties, especially freedom of
speech. Now, let's give some examples of
things that happened in the Red Scare.
Truman's Executive Order 9835, also
known as the Loyalty Order, investigated
government employees for, quote,
disloyalty and led to thousands losing
their jobs. The House on Un-American
Activities Committee investigated
suspected communists with a special
focus on Hollywood, where specifically
in Hollywood, 10 writers, directors, and
screenwriters were cited and blacklisted
from the industry. And finally, there
were actual real espionage cases, such
as Alger Hiss, but the more dramatic one
here was probably the Rosenbergs, where
after these two were convicted of
selling secrets to the Soviet Union,
they were executed by electric chair.
But moving on, by the end of the '50s,
pushback against McCarthyism, such as
criticism by Margaret Chase Smith, will
inevitably cause paranoia to die down
and the whole Red Scare by the end of
the '50s will essentially dissipate. But
just remember, even though people argued
about methods, both political parties in
this era agreed that communism must be
stopped. So, World War
from an economic standpoint, after World
War II, America goes through massive
economic growth and there is a lot of
reasons for this. Large corporations
expand rapidly, meaning more goods are
produced and more of a consumer economy
develops. Also of note is that the
federal government played a major role
in boosting the economy. Let's go
through a few very important things. The
GI Bill provided all these millions of
World War II veterans with money for
college, housing, and business loans.
And the Interstate Highway Act launched
a massive road-building project, the
reason there are all of these highways
around the country. So, with the economy
being strong, people wanted more babies
and that's where we see a massive spike
in the birth rate post-World War II
known as the baby boom. And more people
in the world means more of a demand for
houses and goods, which is where we see
all of these technologies on the screen
being manufactured in this time period,
which contributed more to the greater
economic boom. So, now we see a couple
of things. The country's economy is very
strong, goods are being bought and sold
at high levels, and now there are roads
all over the place. So, the result of
this will be a lot of migration.
Specifically, millions of middle-class
Americans moved from big cities to
suburbs. The reason for this is pretty
simple, roads make transportation way
faster, there is affordable housing with
FHA loans in the GI Bill, and also lots
of houses are being built. And the thing
I want to reference here is
mass-produced neighborhoods full of
houses that look the exact same, which
was very common in this time period
known as a Levittown. A good area where
people migrated to was the Sun Belt, all
because of the recently invented air
conditioning, which made living in this
hot region more plausible. However,
despite all of the economic
improvements, you have to understand
that you had to be a very specific skin
color to get access to these
improvements. That's right,
government-backed housing policies often
excluded minorities. This was known as
redlining, by the way, and this would
mean suburban growth was racially
unequal. Take a look at this man. He
looks pretty cool. But then, take a look
at the guy next to him. It's the same
damn person. Yeah, that's right. This is
basically the 1950s in American history.
The reason I say that is because during
the '50s, people across the country
started living very similar lives,
meaning American culture became
increasingly homogeneous. Now, it's
pretty easy to see why this is the case.
The television becomes massive and every
American is watching them. And to add to
that, TV shows promote a nuclear family,
meaning where the husband works and the
wife stays at home. Shows also showed
suburban life and traditional gender
roles. So, now everyone is watching and
being influenced by the same things.
But, it's not just that. The economic
boom of the '50s also means everyone is
buying the same stuff, such as cars,
appliances, and again, TVs. And now with
Americans living in the suburbs, again,
remember, this is what an American
neighborhood looks like. It's all the
same. So, when you look at the '50s in
American history from a cultural
standpoint, the big label you can truly
give it is calling it conformist,
meaning people are following the same
norms, expectations, and lifestyles.
Now, though what I said is all true, it
wasn't technically all the same. There
is some pushback against conformity in
this time period. Let's go through some
examples. The Beat Movement happened,
where writers and poets rejected
consumerism and traditional values. Rock
and roll surged with artists like Chuck
Berry and Elvis Presley. I mean, listen
to this song by Elvis.
Sorry, that's all I can play so I don't
get copyrighted. The last two things
here are intellectual criticism of
aspects of American culture. And also,
there were early movements in the LGBTQ+
movement, with an example being the
Mattachine Society, which were one of
the earliest, most influential US gay
rights organizations. Hello there. To
start this video, I want to flashback to
my final Unit 5 video where I said this.
Reconstruction was the US's first
attempt at civil rights and it failed
miserably. But, the 14th and 15th
Amendments didn't go away. They became
the legal foundation for the Civil
Rights Movement 100 years later. So,
yeah, it's finally 100 years later and
it's time to talk about the Civil Rights
Movement. So, let's look at a typical
group of black Americans in the 1950s.
You might be surprised to know this, but
at this time, blacks were legally forced
to go to separate schools, use different
bathrooms and water fountains, sit in
the back of buses, and were often
blocked from voting, certain jobs, and
even neighborhoods, all because of the
color of their skin. So, now, a lot of
black soldiers fought for freedom in
World War and then they come back to
legally sanctioned segregation at home.
This was not sustainable anymore. So,
the big African-American rights
organization, the NAACP, went for a very
specific strategy to combat segregation.
And that strategy was challenging
segregation in courts, with a big lawyer
in this regard being Thurgood Marshall.
And this will all lead to our three
branches of government acting, albeit at
different times. In the executive
branch, Truman will desegregate the
military. In the judicial, the very
important Brown vs. Board of Education
case happens, which declared school
segregation as unconstitutional, meaning
it overturned Plessy v. Ferguson's
separate but equal doctrine. And
finally, in the legislative branch, the
Civil Rights Act of 1957 was passed. It
was pretty weak and didn't really do
much, but it is symbolic as the first
civil rights law since Reconstruction.
So, now we see this civil rights
movement expand. For example, courts
became key battlegrounds for arguing
civil rights. And obviously, we have our
two main civil rights organizations. And
who can forget the lady who refused to
give up her seat on a Montgomery bus?
That's right, Rosa Parks and Claudette
Colvin. Oh, and I guess Rosa Parks also
did it, too. Rosa Parks got arrested for
not giving up her bus seat to a white
man, the black community in Montgomery
responded by boycotting the entire bus
system, causing it to lose a lot of
money, with a key figure growing here
being Martin Luther King Jr. This will
lead to bus segregation being ruled
unconstitutional in Browder v. Gayle.
And finally, in a Little Rock, Arkansas,
nine black students enrolled at a
previously all-white high school. The
governor of Arkansas didn't like this
and tried to block these students from
entering school by sending in the
National Guard to block them. And
violent racism erupted as crowds
protested their entry. So, despite Brown
v. Board ruling segregation illegal,
Arkansas didn't care. So, President
Dwight D. Eisenhower had to act. So,
what he did was take control of the
National Guard away from the governor of
Arkansas, and even sent his own troops
to ensure the students could enter the
school safely. It's been a second since
we've talked about it, so let's head on
over back to the Cold War. Last time we
talked a lot about the Cold War in
Europe and also in the US, but now the
Cold War will expand to all over the
world. Let's first head over to Latin
America. And really quickly, the key
point I want to make here before I talk
about anything is that the US will
support any government that is
anti-communist, even if it's not
democratic. So, over in Guatemala, the
US sees a leader who makes
controversial, potentially
communist-influenced land reform. So,
the CIA helps overthrow him. Over in
Chile, a socialist democracy is made
with another democratically elected guy,
and so the US supported his coup d'état.
But it's not all sunshine and rainbows.
Cuba was a country directly aligned with
the Soviet Union. So, the US decides to
launch an invasion known as the Bay of
Pigs. And through a lot of reasons, it
completely fails. But now, moving over
to Africa and the Middle East, most of
these newly [music] formed countries
tried to stay out of the Cold War,
meaning they were \quote} non-aligned.
However, the US still intervened a bit.
The US will help overthrow a leader in
Iran, help negotiate peace between Egypt
and Israel, and in Angola, there was a
proxy war between the USSR and the US.
Honestly, it's a dang chess match. That
is the best way I can describe the Cold
War. But unlike a chess match, there
were actual consequences. And that was
the nuclear threat of a fear of
annihilation. That is where a concept of
MAD is declared, which means mutually
assured destruction, meaning if one side
launches nukes, the other side is going
to do the same. Sure, this does prevent
war, but it will also lead to a massive
arms build-up, and debates around
America will spark up about spending in
the military. This will even lead to
Eisenhower warning about the \quote}
military-industrial complex, where he
warned that government plus military
plus corporations held way too much
power in the United States. So, this
Cold War is intense in many ways, but it
is not over by a long shot, and it's
time to talk about one of its biggest
conflicts, which was the Vietnam War.
So, let's look at a map of Southeast
Asia. After defeating France, Vietnam
split into the communist north under Ho
Chi Minh and the non-communist South
Vietnam. And almost immediately, the two
sides go to war. The US's thinking here
will be the domino theory, which was the
belief that if Vietnam fell to
communism, other Southeast Asian
countries would follow. So, the US
essentially just wanted to contain
communism's spread. So, it starts off
pretty simple. The US will start by
sending money and advisers, but then the
Gulf of Tonkin incident happens, where
two US boats are attacked by North
Vietnam. Now, in retrospect, this
incident was very exaggerated and parts
of it were likely made up, but it didn't
really matter because it caused the
president of the time, Lyndon B.
Johnson, to use the incident to justify
full military involvement in Vietnam by
the US. And so, the US will officially
enter Vietnam. It will implement a full
military draft and send hundreds of
thousands of untrained young boys to
fight, and it will quickly become a
full-on war. Once the US is fully
involved in Vietnam, the war quickly
becomes a nightmare because it isn't a
traditional fight. Communist soldiers
who supported the north but fought in
the south were called the Viet Cong, and
they do not operate like regular
soldiers. Instead, they move within
South Vietnam, using the Ho Chi Minh
Trail for supplies. They blend in with
civilians and rely on ambushes, booby
traps, and tunnel systems. This makes it
incredibly difficult for millions of US
soldiers to tell who the enemy is. So,
then you see a few things happen. The
Tet Offensive happens in Vietnam, where
North Vietnamese soldiers launch a
massive series of surprise attacks on
the south. And then the Pentagon Papers
get released, showing that US leaders
had been secretly expanding and
misrepresenting the war, while lying to
the public saying that things were under
control. And finally, the My Lai
Massacre happens, where US soldiers
killed hundreds of unarmed Vietnamese
civilians. All of these combined
together caused the US public to most
openly despise this war. The result here
is college protests, widespread draft
resistance, and cultural divide. This
will lead to the War Powers Act, which
basically said that the president can't
just drag the US into war without
Congress. And finally, when Nixon
becomes president, he begins pulling US
soldiers out of Vietnam until finally,
in 1975, the US officially exits the
war. North Vietnam wins, and Vietnam
becomes communist. How about that? For
once in history, the US actually loses.
But back over in America, even though
the economy was booming by the '60s,
people start realizing that not everyone
is benefiting. A book that acted as a
very good exposé was The Other America
by Michael Harrington. Basically, this
book revealed that there was a hidden
poverty in America, revealing the
struggles of millions of poor Americans.
And then on top of this, because of the
result of World War II and the economic
boom of the '50s, by the 1960s, American
citizens have almost full confidence in
its own liberal government and thinks
the government can solve social issues.
This will all lead President Lyndon B.
Johnson to enact his Great Society,
which was an expansion of the New Deal
focused on social issues rather than
just the economy, aiming to end poverty,
reduce racial inequality, improve
education, and expand health care. Let's
go over the things the Great Society
created. Programs focusing on poverty
will be implemented, such as the Job
Corps for job training, Head Start for
early childhood education, and the Food
Stamp Act for food assistance.
Healthcare programs will also be
implemented, such as Medicare for the
elderly and Medicaid for the poor. It's
also important to note that this plan
for a Great Society often worked
alongside the ongoing civil rights
movement at the time. The other part to
this though is immigration. And we see
this with the Immigration Act of 1965,
where finally quotas are removed,
meaning we see a lot more immigration
from Latin America and Asia, which
permanently changed US demographics. So,
you might be asking now, was this Great
Society a good success or bad overall?
Well, it obviously did have successes
that we still see in our society to this
day, but I want you to understand
something. Remember the Gilded Age,
where America had a very small
government and didn't intervene in its
economy at all? Remember the whole
laissez-faire thing? Now, we have gone
through the New Deal, World War II, and
now the Great Society. So, the result is
the US government is as big as it has
ever been, and it is intervening as much
in its own economy as it ever has.
Conservatives on the right will argue
that the government is way too big now.
And later, past the '70s into the '80s,
things like Vietnam and a lot of
government spending will cause mass
inflation and unemployment, leading to a
growing distrust in government and a
resulting age of conservatism, but I get
ahead of myself. It's time to talk about
the official African-American Civil
Rights Movement. We already talked about
the roots of this with Rosa Parks, the
bus boycott, and the Little Rock Nine,
but pretty quickly, the movement expands
even bigger. So, here is what you need
to know. During the early part of the
Civil Rights Movement in the '60s, the
overall goal was non-violent protest,
because violence would undermine the
goal of the movement. The leader of this
movement will be a man named Martin
Luther King Jr. So, why don't we go
through some examples of this movement?
Sit-ins were protests where black
activists sat at segregated lunch
counters, refusing to leave until
served. Freedom Rides happened where
people of many races sat in white-only
sections of buses throughout the south
to challenge segregation. And finally,
there were a lot of marches in big
cities. For example, in the March on
Washington, Martin Luther King Jr. went
up on a stage and gave his I Have a
Dream speech, where he pleaded to
thousands of people about his dreams of
a world without blatant segregation. And
it would easily become one of the most
famous speeches in world history. And by
this point, the non-violent movement had
gotten so big that it finally pushed
real federal action. The 1964 Civil
Rights Act is passed, which completely
ends segregation and bans
discrimination. The Voting Rights Act is
also passed, which protected black
voting rights. And also, the other two
branches of government do a few things
as well. Here is the issue though,
because even if the federal government
passed all these laws, poverty still
exists, racism still exists, and urban
violence actually steadily rises. And
this is where the Civil Rights Movement
will essentially split in half. On one
side, you have the Martin Luther
King-inspired non-violent protest, but
now on the other side, you have a
growing group of people advocating for
more aggressive measures like
self-defense, black pride, and economic
independence. A leader to reference here
is Malcolm X. This second movement based
on black power gets really popular and
leads to groups like the Black Panthers,
who again advocate for more aggressive
measures. It's also important to note
that these two very important leaders
will get assassinated, which definitely
does not help the non-violent side of
things. So, there is an obvious split
here, and this will mean by the midpoint
of the '60s, the civil rights movement
is not necessarily one thing anymore. It
is a movement divided behind different
methods, full of a lot of ongoing
struggles. So, this African-American
civil rights movement has gotten really
big by the '60s. So, the big idea here
is all these other groups of minorities
are seeing the success of this big
movement and are getting inspired to do
something similar with their group. We
have five groups to go over in this
video, so let's get into it. Latinos
will start the Chicano movement, where
leaders like Cesar Chavez will form the
United Farm Workers to fight low wages
and poor working conditions. An example
of things they did were non-violent
things such as a national consumer
boycott of California table grapes. This
will lead to union contracts, better
wages, and safer working conditions.
Moving on though, American Indians
formed their own movement as well. The
goal here was to reclaim their own
rights and [music] protest government
treatment. The two big things that
happened here were that Native American
groups would forcibly occupy the prison
Alcatraz and the town of Wounded Knee in
an effort to protest the federal
government. But now let's move over to
Asian Americans. This one was more
focused on giving Asians their own
identity in America. And lots of what
you see here are college protests
against anti-Asian racism. Now let's
move over to feminism. If you remember
in the past, we had our era of
first-wave feminism. Now we are in the
technical second wave, where women are
going to advocate for full equal rights
such as equal pay, workplace equality,
and an equal rights amendment. An
organization here popularized was the
National Organization for Women or NOW.
And a really important book made here
was Betty Friedan's The Feminine
Mystique, which exposed the lack of
fulfillment an American housewife truly
has. And finally, the LGBTQ+ community
had their own movement as well to try
and fight discrimination and demand
recognition. A key turning point in this
movement was the Stonewall riots, which
would eventually lead to a later gay
liberation movement. Let's go over a few
things right now. The Vietnam War is
causing millions of young men to be
drafted, the Pentagon Papers has exposed
the government lies, and caused a mass
distrust,
and the civil rights movement is proving
that protesting can work to change the
norm. And so, the result we see here is
the youngsters of society starting to
question authority and rebel. We already
talked about instances of this like
college protests and marches, but a very
important event I haven't mentioned is
the Kent State massacre, where a large
group of students at Kent State
University were protesting Vietnam. One
thing led to another, and four people
ended up being shot and killed by the US
National Guard in the crowd. But moving
on, now what we see is a new variation
of left in society called the Students
for a Democratic Society, who believed
the government wasn't doing enough
socially, but was too aggressive
militarily. This group criticized things
like war, inequality, and government
power. And the final form of this youth
culture is the formation of a
counterculture social rebellion. This is
where you see the hippies of the '60s
rejecting traditional jobs, gender
roles, and materialism. This will create
a more rebellious informal society. Here
is a good way to remember the hippie
movement. Peace, love, sex, and a whole
lot of grass, which is slang for lots
and lots and lots of drugs. So, in this
time period, finally it is realized by
American society that the environment
essentially exists. The reason behind
this is because a lot of bad
environment-related things happened all
at once. This river, which I'm not going
to pronounce the name of, literally
caught on fire. This town was built upon
a bunch of toxic waste causing a surge
of diseases such as cancer, and this
power plant almost completely melted
down. And from all of this, people start
to realize industrial growth just might
be messing up the environment. Oh, but
it gets worse. Of course, what I'm
referring to here is the energy crisis,
where basically there was severe fuel
shortages in the Middle East the US
depended on, causing prices at gas
stations to spike and for there to be
historically long gas station lines.
This will all finally cause some
environmental action. Let's go through
some examples. The Environmental
Protection Agency will be created, Air
Act will limit emissions, and the
Endangered Species Act will protect
endangered animals/plants. As for
energy, the Department of Energy will be
created, and the US will shift to focus
more on energy independence. The 1950s
and 1960s. There is a big word I want to
throw out there and say trust, because
these two eras of American history saw
many people trust the American liberal
government. And now I want to put it
bluntly as we are in the '70s, the
optimism of the '50s and early '60s is
now gone. [music]
Vietnam is an utter failure and causes
people to distrust the government. But
then the truly infamous Watergate
scandal happens, where President Richard
Nixon covers up a burglary at the
Democratic National Committee
headquarters, revealing widespread
illegal surveillance and political
sabotage leading to Nixon's presidential
resignation in 1974. And not to mention,
the 1970s American economy had high
inflation and growing unemployment,
which is a very rare economic phenomenon
called stagflation. When we get into
Jimmy Carter's presidency, it doesn't
get much better. The energy crisis moves
into full effect, a hostage crisis in
Iran made the government appear
ineffective, and now by this point,
distrust in the United States government
by its own citizens is at an all-time
high. The liberals in society have
dominated the political landscape for so
long now, dating all the way back to the
New Deal. But now with this combination
of things, conservatives are going to
rise through the cracks. Conservatives
will have an ideology of thinking the
government is way too big, so they want
less regulation, a stronger military,
and a pushback to traditional values.
Not to mention, you also see a rise of
evangelical Christianity, which will
become more intertwined with politics,
specifically intertwining with the
conservative side. This will lead to the
'80s later, where conservatism will take
over. Hey, and thank you so much for
watching. Please do now consider
watching this video and subscribing to
this channel, which is my
non-educational channel. Um, I'm not
actually sure what I'm supposed to say
here. It's honestly kind of weird. This
video's audio quality kind of dropped
halfway through. I'm not even sure why
that happened, but you know, that's all
for me though. I'll see you guys.